And שנה טובה Shana Tova and גוט וואך, Gut vuch, we're now
actually into the rest of the year. We pick up on today's
דף daf is officially ט"ו. Tes-Vav. We are a bit behind. Hopefully
we'll be able to catch up a good deal today. We pick
up on י"ד עמוד א' Yud-Dalid Amud Aleph and תא שמע, Tashma,
it is four lines before the lines get wide. The basic question
started from a general question רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish asked רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan by different people reading מגילת Megillat
at different times, isn't there a need for consistency of practice? Meaning
what about the problem of לא תתגודדו אגודות אגודות? Lo tishgodedu agudot
agudot? And that has led now, that is a particularly interesting הלכה
halacha where actually according to the הלכה, halacha, different people do different
things. But that has led to a broader discussion of the issue
of do we allow there to be a difference of פסק psak
opinions and different people following different פסקים, psakim, or do we demand
and look for a consistency of פסק? psak? And this has become
a question of, like one פסק psak for everyone, and this has
become the question sort of of, which isn't necessarily exactly the same
question, but anyway, the question of whether בית שמאי Beit Shammai in
the end wound up following the פסק psak of בית הלל. Beit
Hillel. It's an interesting question whether it means before the בת קול
Bas Kol or after the בת קול, Bas Kol, but certainly at
a point where there was a reasonable reason to think that the
הלכה halacha is like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, but בית שמאי Beit
Shammai could have been in a position to say that no, they
feel the הלכה halacha should still be like them. So was there
this idea of giving up your own פסק psak and going like
a consensus majority פסק psak or maintaining your own פסק, psak, and
also for people, did people feel they had to follow only one,
could people choose which פסק psak they would follow? And the גמרא
Gemara basically has said how would you maintain if
that was true about the problem of לא תתגודדו? Lo tishgodedu? How
would that not be a problem of לא תתגודדו? Lo tishgodedu? And
the גמרא Gemara says, well לא תתגודדו Lo tishgodedu is only different
people in the same place. But if they're different communities in different
places, that would be okay. Although as we pointed out yesterday, that's
a little bit ironic because that exactly creates a sense of factions,
of breaking people up, balkanizing. This community does that one, this place
does that one. But anyway, at least you're not competing within the
same place, and within the same place there is a uniformity of
practice. But then the גמרא Gemara said, well בית הלל, בית שמאי
Beis Hillel Beis Shammai, also is the same geographic location. Now you
could have tried to say the difference had to do with a
concept of community even though it's not geographically different, and that's certainly
things that we have very much nowadays. In the time of the
גמרא, Gemara, you very much had things defined by geography, מנהג המקום
Minhag Hamakom and so on. Nowadays where everybody moves around all the
place and so on, you know, you have more of a virtual
community idea. But anyway, that was the גמרא's Gemara question, you don't
have there distinct geographic locations. And that led to רבא's Rava assertion
that you don't even need distinct geographic locations. It's not לא תתגודדו
Lo tishgodedu if people are following different פסקים. psakim. It's basically only
לא תתגודדו Lo tishgodedu if a בית דין beis din has not
come up with a פסק, psak, that the בית דין beis din
is conflicted and therefore everybody is doing whatever they want. That's sort
of like anarchy. But if you genuinely have different פסקים psakim and
different people follow different פסקים, psakim, that's not לא תתגודדו. Lo tishgodedu.
So that approach, which we ended with, is a pretty radical rejection
of לא תתגודדו, Lo tishgodedu, right? You can just follow different פסקים,
psakim, but in a way that is also what we find nowadays,
people follow different פסקים psakim and so on, but you don't even
need a concept of a community. Okay, now that seems a little
extreme, again, you know, somewhere between אביי Abaye and רבא Rava seems
to be a more comfortable position where you don't need necessarily a
different geographic location, but you do need a sense of like different
communities, even if they're virtual communities, do different things. But we have
pretty much limited לא תתגודדו Lo tishgodedu pretty radically
and the only question now we're left with, or the only thing
we're still trying to resolve is what do we think למעשה Lema'aseh
happened with בית הלל, בית שמאי, Beit Hillel Beit Shammai has בית
שמאי Beit Shammai chosen to follow בית הלל Beit Hillel, or not?
And again, this could be a general debate in all areas of
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, which is what we're
going to look at. Of course all the evidence points to the
fact that בית שמאי Beit Shammai stuck to their guns. However, the
reason this seems particularly an issue, forget לא תתגודדו, Lo tishgodedu, it
seems that this is particularly an issue because of the challenge of
the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna pointed out that the women of
בית הלל Beit Hillel should be אסור assur to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, and
nevertheless they intermarry. And that's like a radical, and that's like a
radical idea. How could they intermarry? Isn't, aren't these women אסור assur
to me? So by saying בית שמאי Beit Shammai, basically practiced like
בית הלל, Beit Hillel עשו כדברי בית הלל, asu k'divrei Beit Hillel,
that is a way of resolving or taming, neutralizing the radical statement
of the משנה. Mishna. And it's important to keep that in mind
that that's what also is what's relevant here beyond questions of לא
תתגודדו. Lo tishgodedu. But this is the issue now that we return
to, which is did בית שמאי Beit Shammai follow the practices in
general of בית הלל Beit Hillel, or not? Yes, Michael.
Just thinking regarding the מגילה, Megilla, then we said that wasn't a
problem because
there was a defined פסק. psak. Right, so that's a good point.
So the גמרא Gemara never gets back to how it solved the
מגילה Megilla problem. תוספות Tosfos basically says once you introduced the idea
of two בתי דינים batei dinim in two places, or of even
two בתי דינים batei dinim in one place, the idea of מגילה
Megilla also is not problematic because basically there actually,
that's. But as to try to actually make it more literally two
places, תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos* says an idea that's a pretty big of
a shocker for those that learn מגילה Megillah *Megillah*, and he actually
says maybe the the people from the villages actually read on the
11th, 12th, and 13th in the village, not in the city, because
for them to be reading in the city would be like two
בתי דינים *batei dinim* in one place. Okay, which is pretty wild,
because we've always assumed they come into the city for the market
day anyway.
You don't have a ספר *sefer*, you
don't even know how to read? Exactly. Anyway, the ראש *Rosh* says
otherwise. All right, let's get back now to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
תא שמע ta shma *ta shema*.
Four lines before the lines get wide on י"א ע"ב *yod aleph
amud beis*. תא שמע ta shma *ta shema*, come and hear. במקומו
של רבי אליעזר *bimkomo shel Rabbi Eliezer*, now we're not even going
to deal with בית הלל Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis
Hillel Beis Shammai* just, although רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is from בית
שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai*, but again we're dealing with the we've
broadened this question about whether people were allowed to maintain their own
פסק psak *psak* position or did they have to concede to the
majority? Okay. במקומו של רבי אליעזר היו כורתים עצים לעשות פחמים בשבת
לעשות ברזל *bimkomo shel Rabbi Eliezer hayu korsim eitzim la'asos pechamim b'Shabbos
la'asos barzel*. So in the place of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says you could not only do the act of
מילה *milah* on שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos* if it was an eighth day
מילה *milah*, but you could do מכשירי מילה *machshirei milah*, anything needed
to prepare and get the implements ready and get everything to make
it possible. So they would actually cut down trees in order to
make a in order to make a fire to make coals in
order to in order to shape the metal for the for the
knife for מילה *milah* on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, which seems pretty wild.
And if you look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, he says במקומו של
רבי אליעזר *bimkomo shel Rabbi Eliezer*, דבמתכוין היו מביאים עצמם שהיו צריכים
לכך משום חיבוב מצווה *d'bimiskavein hayu mevi'im atzmam she-hayu tzerichim l'kach mishum
chivuv mitzvah*. They wanted to show how important ברית מילה *bris milah*
was that it could override all of these restrictions, that they actually
made a point of doing all of this on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*
for the to show the strength of of ברית מילה *bris milah*.
So that was his פסק psak. *psak*. Of course, we don't פסקן
pasken *pasken* that way. We פסקן pasken *pasken* only מילה *milah* itself.
במקומו של רבי יוסי הגלילי היו אוכלים בשר עוף בחלב *bimkomo shel
Rabbi Yosi HaGelili hayu ochlim basar of b'chalav*. In רבי יוסי הגלילי's
*Rabbi Yosi HaGelili's* place they would eat they would eat what's that
called chicken chicken stroganoff or there was another one I knew that
was with with milk. Chicken parmesan. Anyway, because he said now now
that's really not a דאורייתא *d'oraisa* thing. Yeah, pretty much everybody agrees
right? Because you know the way you tell people you know what
many people assume you know that chicken fowl is בשר בחלב *basar
b'chalav*, it's meat. He says yeah but you know just point out
it doesn't have mother's milk.
So clearly it's not in the פסוק *posuk*. But the point is
we hold that it's rabbinically forbidden. He held that it was not
rabbinically forbidden and he maintains his position and the people of his
place maintain his position. So here you really have this idea of
at least שתי מקומות *shte mikomos* that in different geographic locations they
can follow different positions. And also the issue was raised yesterday, you
know the idea of like a מסורה *mesorah* following a certain פסק
psak, *psak* because it's your tradition. So or you know because your
רבי *Rebbe* says it. So here it wasn't just random places follow
these פסקים psakim. *psakim*, the actual place of the רב *Rav* followed
that פסק psak. *psak*. Okay. במקומו של רבי אליעזר אין במקומו של
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's לא *bimkomo shel Rabbi Eliezer in bimkomo shel
Rabbi Akiva lo*. So they would only follow in רבי אליעזר's מקום
*Rabbi Eliezer's makom*. They wouldn't follow it in רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
מקום *Rabbi Akiva's makom*. דתנן *d'tnan*, כלל אמר רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva,
כל מלאכה שאפשר לעשותה מערב שבת Shabbat אינה דוחה את השבת *klal
amar Rabbi Akiva kol melacha she'efshar la'asosah me'erev Shabbos einah dochah es
ha'Shabbos*. So any מלאכה *melacha* that you could do at ערב שבת
*erev Shabbos* you can't do on שבת *Shabbos*. So you see that
in רבי אליעזר's *Rabbi Eliezer's* place they would so you know so
you see that number one the point here seems to be not
you see that basically we פסקן paskened *pasken* like it seems to
be the point is we see we פסקן pasken *pasken* like רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*. And even though we generally would פסקן
pasken *pasken* like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* elsewhere, here they would follow
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. Isn't that a problem of לא תתגודדו Lo
Titgodedu? *lo tisgodedu*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והאי מאי תיובתא
*v'hai mai tiyuvta*? Why is that a problem? מקומות מקומות שאני mikomot
mikomot shani *mikomos mikomos shani*. We already got through saying that different
locations can follow different פסקים psakim? *psakim* and it's not a problem.
Everybody agrees to that. I mean רבא Rava *Rava* wanted to say
even one place, but at least we said different places could do
it. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay so that's a good answer.
ודקארי לה מאי קארי לה *u'dekari lah mai kari lah*? So what
were you even thinking? I mean we had already given that answer.
סלקא דעתך אמינא *salqa da'atach amina*, I would have thought משום חומרא
דשבת כחד מקום דמי *mishum chumrah d'Shabbos k'chad makom dami*. שבת *Shabbos*
is so weighty and here and they're actually going to violate שבת
*Shabbos* in רבי אליעזר's מקום *Rabbi Eliezer's makom*, maybe we wouldn't have
allowed that. Maybe we would have insisted on more consistency in practice
when it comes to something as weighty as שבת *Shabbos*. קא משמע
לן Ka mashma lan. *ka mashma lan* that no, that we allow
there to be differences of practice in different locations even in extremely
weighty matters. You know by the way the one thing that you
know we absolutely do not allow for there to be differences in
practice is in practice is the question of when ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh* is. You know when the calendar is. There has to be
one shared you know practice of the holidays. That's really what unifies
the people and that's why obviously you know you had things like
the sect of the Jubilees and the צדוקים *Tzadukim* that really was
things you know about when שבועות *Shavuos* is you know that really
sort of breaks people off as a different type of a people
if they have their holidays on different days. And there was a
whole debate post the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* whether when where the גאונים
*Geonim* of בבל Bavel *Bavel* said it was one date and the
גאונים *Geonim* of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* said it was another. another
date and it was a huge debate and in the end the
גאונים of בבל Bavel won out and that really was like the
מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish like the final thing that indicated that the
seat of authority had moved to בבל Bavel and that the authority
of בבל in areas of
הלכה. Halacha. So the idea of a consistency of practice I mean
this is a very central religious question the גמרא Gemara is asking:
do you allow differences of practice and even in some of the
weightiest areas even in שבת? And the answer is even in תחום
שבת. techum Shabbat. We're not talking about just דרבננס d'rabbanans of שבת.
And the answer is yes we will allow that. We got as
there will be this one area like I said the גמרא Gemara
is saying but I'm telling you like calendar that has to be
uniform but we will actually allowed a divergence of practices. And again
the more it's in different places the more it's like okay that's
that place that's maybe a little that diffuses it a little bit.
It's not like nobody it doesn't create a sense of anarchy that
you get if everybody in a same location is doing wildly different
things.
Yes. And that was why רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was so adamant
about making רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
because exactly exactly yeah.
What was the answer here? עדיפות adifut מקומות מקומות mekomot mekomot meaning
at different places but not within the same...
yeah and we used to talk about בית. Bayit. רבא Rava suggested
even in the same place you could have different practices but certainly
everybody agreed different places could follow different פסקים.
psakim We also we saw a סוגיא sugya where there was an
allowance for two different dates. Not the מגילה Megillah? or maybe it
was מגילה? Megillah.
You're thinking about מגילה. Okay תא שמע Tashma, come and hear.
דרבי אבא de-Rabbi Abba כי אקלע לאתריה דרבי יהושע בן לוי ki
ikla le-asre de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi when רבי אבא Rabbi Abba came
to the place of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
הוי מטלטל שרגא. havi metaltel sharga. He would carry a candle. וכי
אקלע ve-ki ikla now it's not a now the point here is
lamp really it's not a lit lamp that was שבת it was
an extinguished lamp but the question was is an extinguished lamp that
was burning on שבת and then extinguished is that מוקצה muktzeh or
not? Okay so here in the place of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi he would carry
it. וכי אקלע לאתריה דרבי יוחנן ve-ki ikla le-asre de-Rabbi Yochanan when
he came to the place of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not allow you to carry these lamps לא
הוי מטלטל שרגא lo havi metaltel sharga he wouldn't. So you see
anyway that different practices were in force in different places. So the
גמרא Gemara says והאי מאי קושיא ve-hai mai kushia why is it
a problem? ולא אמינא מקומות שאני v'lo amina mikomot shani or מקומות
מקומות mekomot mekomot שאני different places you can have different practices. גמרא
Gemara says no אנן הכי קאמינא anan hachi ka'aminon here's what we're
saying. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba היכי עביד הכי הכא הכא והיכי עביד
הכא הכא? heichi avid hachi hacha hacha ve-heichi avid hacha hacha? How
did רבי אבא Rabbi Abba do one thing in one place and
one thing in the other place? He's the same person so how
is he practicing differently? Of course there's an obvious answer if you
פסקן pasken לחומרא l'chumra you then it's a question how can you
be מיקל meikel in somebody else's place? But if you פסקן pasken
לקולא l'kula okay so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
דרבי אבא כרבי יהושע בן לוי סבירא ליה. de-Rabbi Abba k'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi s'vira leh. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua פסקנס paskens לקולא. l'kula.
וכי אקלע לאתריה דרבי יוחנן ve-ki ikla le-asre de-Rabbi Yochanan but when
he came to the place of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לא הוי
מטלטל משום כבוד דרבי יוחנן lo havi metaltel mishum kvod de-Rabbi Yochanan
he would do it for the honor of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
but it wasn't like he himself what do you mean רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba was in two places? He's one person so how can
you as one person have different פסקים? psakim You don't have different
פסקים psakim I'm מיקל meikel but out of deference to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan I didn't carry it in רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan place.
Even what you do though if it's explicitly contradictory any words from
the...
Alright so that's what we'll so fine so that's what we'll get
to. You mean and you have to do something לכבוד lichvod of
somebody so okay that's interesting. I mean we'll see some of the
things they say. והאיכא שמעא ve-hika shamah but what about his attendant?
His attendant sees him practicing different ways so his attendant might actually
get confused
and the attendant might if you look at רש"י Rashi says דרבי
אבא לא מציקא דעתיה מטלטל בתריה דרבי יוחנן. de-Rabbi Abba lo matika
daiteh metaltel batre de-Rabbi Yochanan. So won't his attendant have seen that
in general רבי אבא Rabbi Abba carries a lamp and then he'll
come to do it also in the place of רבי יוחנן? Rabbi
Yochanan? So it says דמודע ליה לשמעיה de-moda leh le-shamaye fine he
informed him. He said hey we're going to רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
place be careful not to carry a lamp. Fine. Alright תא שמע
Ta shema. come and hear. אף על פי שאלו אוסרים ואלו מתירים.
af al pi she-eilu osrim ve-eilu matirim. Now by the way again
it is interesting again how
אביי Abaye I think it's worth pointing out that when אביי Abaye
says because the גמרא Gemara here seems to be going back to
אביי's Abaye position different places it's okay because רבא's idea that even
in the same place really basically completely rejects the concept altogether and
all for all intents and purposes. But presumably אביי Abaye will still
have to say that that you can have a concept of a
virtual community like this whole idea of בית הלל Beit Hillel and
בית שמאי Beit Shammai right? Presumably
אביי Abaye doesn't need it to be always a different geographic location.
He's allowing for the school of בית הלל Beit Hillel and the
school of בית שמאי Beit Shammai to have different practices presumably in
the same geographic area. So one also does wonder even according to
this idea of מקומות מקומות do we have a concept of different
geography or could it be different communities or even virtual communities within
the same location? We just had חול המועד Chol HaMoed and the
big question comes up how does you allow a שול shul to
have people that are doing that are wearing תפילין tefillin people not
wearing תפילין tefillin in the same in the same מנין? minyan? And
I know some places that insist that people that are wearing תפילין
tefillin דאוון daven in... different מנין minyan and then they join up
like for הלל Hallel or something like that. Does that make it
better or less, more or less לא תתגודדו? Again, the idea of
keeping separate
removes anarchy, creates a consistency in one place, but it certainly fractionalizes.
So it's again interesting that the גמרא's Gemara preferring this idea of
מקום מקום, makom makom, and the question I'm raising is, can because
of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, can it
also be a sense of a virtual community? Okay.
Let's learn some תורה Torah in a different vein.
You mean, yeah, right, that's also true. בני ארץ ישראל Bnei Eretz
Yisrael and בני חוץ לארץ. Bnei Chutz La'aretz. Yeah. What? In שול
shul because of the Israeli מנין. minyan. All right, anyway, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע, ta shema אף על
פי שאלו אוסרין ואלו מתירין, af al pi she'elu ossrin ve'elu mattirin,
even though these forbid and these permit, back to our משנה: Mishnah:
לא נמנעו בית שמאי מלישא נשים מבית הלל ולא בית הלל מבית
שמאי. lo nimne'u Beit Shammai milissa nashim miBeit Hillel vilo Beit Hillel
miBeit Shammai. So before we said, well, maybe בית שמאי Beit Shammai
actually practiced like בית הלל, Beit Hillel but now we're going to
question that. אי אמרת בשלמא לא עשו, Iy amrat bishlama lo assu,
now we're back to this question of what did בית הלל Beit
Hillel, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai specifically, did בית שמאי Beit Shammai
practice like בית הלל? Beit Hillel If you say that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai did not follow their practices and they
basically acted like בית הלל, Beit Hillel? משום הכי לא נמנעו, mishum
hachi lo nimne'u, that's why they could intermarry. אלא אי אמרת עשו,
Ella iy amrat assu, but if they followed their own practices, אמאי
לא נמנעו? amai lo nimne'u? How could they not intermarry?
בשלמא—I Bishlama mean, how could they not withhold themselves? How could they
intermarry? בשלמא בית שמאי מבית הלל לא נמנעו, Bishlama Beit Shammai miBeit
Hillel lo nimne'u, I can understand that בית שמאי Beit Shammai did
not hold themselves back from marrying into
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, why? דבני חייבי לאוין נינהו, dibney chayvei lavin
ninhu, because according to בית הלל Beit Hillel, the worst you'll have
is a צרה tzarah who בית שמאי Beit Shammai thinks is obligated
in חליצה chalitzah and ייבום yibbum and בית הלל Beit Hillel says
is not, and this צרה tzarah goes and marries some guy, some
foreign guy. That's a לאו, lav, right? That a woman who's obligated
in ייבום yibbum from בית שמאי's Beit Shammai perspective can't marry somebody
who's not the יבם yabam without חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. Then there's a
child. Well, the child that's an offspring of an איסור לאו issur
lav is not a ממזר. mamzer. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai has
very little to be concerned about in terms of בית הלל. Beit
Hillel So the צרות tzaros went and they married without חליצה chalitzah
a different person, fine, the child is okay, so there's very little
to be concerned about. Now what you have to be concerned about
is that they might actually marry the צרה tzarah herself, they don't
want to be עובר over on
a לאו. lav. Okay, but let's read the answer and then I'll
get back to that question in one minute. It says, דבני חייבי
לאוין נינהו. dibney chayvei lavin ninhu. אלא
בית הלל מבית שמאי אמאי לא נמנעו? Ella Beit Hillel miBeit Shammai
amai lo nimne'u? But if the houses kept their different practice, how
could בית הלל Beit Hillel. not hold themselves back from בית שמאי?
Beit Shammai? Because בית הלל Beit Hillel thinks that this צרה tzarah
is פטור patur in ייבום yibbum and בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
doing ייבום yibbum with the צרה, tzarah, which is an איסור כרת
issur kares and the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. So how could בית
הלל Beit Hillel marry into בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? מבית
שמאי אמאי לא נמנעו בני חייבי כריתות ממזרים נינהו, miBeit Shammai amai
lo nimne'u bney chayvei kerisos mamzerim ninhu, they're ממזרים. mamzerim. וכי תימא
קסבר בית הלל דאין ממזר מחייבי כריתות? vekhi teima kasvar Beit Hillel
de'ein mamzer mechayvei kerisos? Maybe בית הלל Beit Hillel holds that a
person would not be a ממזר mamzer from חייבי כריתות? chayvei kerisos?
And if you're not a ממזר mamzer from חייבי כריתות, chayvei kerisos,
what would you be? מחייבי מיתה, mechayvei missa, which would basically be
adultery or cases like mother and daughter. Okay, but lateral relations, not.
So maybe they hold—and there is an opinion like that—so maybe they
hold the kids wouldn't be ממזרים. mamzerim.
והאמר רבי אלעזר אף על פי שנחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל בצרות,
veha'amar Rabbi Elazar af al pi shenechleku Beit Shammai uBeit Hillel betzaros,
even though they disagreed with the status of the צרות, tzaros, מודין
שאין ממזר אלא ממי שאיסורו איסור ערוה ועונש כרת. modin she'ein mamzer
ella mim mi she'issuro issur ervah ve'onash kares. They hold that there's
no ממזר mamzer except from an איסור כרת. issur kares. So basically
בית הלל Beit Hillel would hold that these kids would be ממזרים.
mamzerim. How could it be that they would marry in, assuming the
people kept their different practices? So now you see the reason to
say they didn't keep their practices because that would answer the radical
statement of the משנה. Mishnah. But then the משנה Mishnah is not
saying too much. Unless it's saying, yeah, exactly. But if you're saying
that they kept their practices, which is obviously the פשט, pshat, then
how do you explain the radical statement of the משנה? Mishnah? אלא
לאו שמע מינה לא עשו, Ella lav shma mina lo assu, must
be they didn't keep their practices.
And maybe that's the חידוש chiddush of the משנה, Mishnah, that in
order to create uniform practices, בית שמאי Beit Shammai gave in to
בית הלל. Beit Hillel That would presumably be the חידוש. chiddush. But
obviously it's not the פשט. pshat. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא
לעולם עשו. lo le'olam assu. No, בית שמאי Beit Shammai kept their
practice. But how do you explain how they intermarried? דמודיעי להו ופרשי,
demodei'ei lehu ufarshi, that they were understanding enough, they were sympathetic enough
to not—that it wouldn't create a fight between them, but they said,
look, בית הלל, Beit Hillel. I understand you want to marry so-and-so,
you should know she's actually the daughter of a צרה, tzarah, da
da da da da, they would share the information because they would
respect one another's position. So it didn't mean that they would
have to be concerned about it. Of course they'd have to be
concerned about it, but there was so much positive and mutual respect
that they would go out of their way to inform one another
about what the story would be in order that—and you have that
nowadays, right? Some people say,
you're eating in my house, how dare you not trust my כשרות?
kashrus? And other people say, I want you to know, I use
this and I do that, maybe it's not the same פסק psak
as you have, and you have this idea that you can be
sort of you have this mutual— of respect and you'll be happy
to share with the other person what the information is and that's
the חידוש Chidush of the משנה Mishna but not that they actually
would intermarry. Okay, that's without being oblivious or unconcerned of the fact.
The טהרה? Tahara? They go מכלי? mi-keili?
And the גמרא Gemara is going to get to the טהרה. Tahara.
Just a quick question: if they're going to keep track for ten
generations?
What? Yeah, that's a good question. You'd really have to... well, no,
you wouldn't have to keep
track... yeah, it's the case of the ממזר mamzer you'd have to
really, really keep track. That's an excellent point, you know, for... not
the צרה tzara case, not for בית שמאי's Beit Shammai would have
to keep track because the ממזרות mamzeirus would keep on going. That's
an excellent point.
I recall the Ethiopian community, I think I recall an exhibit they
had certain people who memorized... Oh, really?
Everybody's genealogy?
...come to them and ask if they can marry.
Wow, fascinating, fascinating. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai here, if you look
at the little תוספות, Tosafot בשם מי בית שמאי לא נמנו, Be-shem
mi Beit Shammai lo nimnu, תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר ואמאי לא
נמנו משום צרה עצמה, Ve-im tomar ve-amai lo nimnu mishum tzara atzma,
but בית שמאי Beit Shammai can't marry the women of בית הלל
Beit Hillel, if because maybe the woman herself is a צרה. tzara.
So why isn't it also that question?
כי דאמרינן לקמן בשמונה עשרה. Ki d-amrina lekaman bi-shmoneh esrei. ויש לומר
Ve-yesh lomar says and you could say דצרה עצמה לא שכיחא כולי
האי. de-tzara atzma lo shechicha kulei hai. Why not?
כמו בני צרות. Kemo bnei tzaros. A צרה tzara is not as
prevalent as the children of
the צרות. tzaros. שאישה אחת יולדת כמה בנים She-isha achas yoledes kama
banim because for every one צרה tzara you can have ten kids.
So therefore there's more of a concern of the kids than of
the woman herself. All right, anyway, but that's the גמרא's Gemara answer:
they inform. So two ways of dealing with the radical חידוש Chidush
of the משנה. Mishna. One is that בית שמאי Beit Shammai can
keep by their position and the other is that everybody informed everybody
else. Now I want to get back to that but let's read
a little bit more.
It says they would be ממזרים. mamzeirim.
No, בני חייבי לאוין bnei chayvei lavin are not ממזרים. mamzeirim. בית
שמאי's Beit Shammai side there, that's why they would inform. That's what
the גמרא Gemara says, that's why they would inform.
Then the children of the צרה tzara would be a problem.
Yes,
and that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, והכי נמי מסתברא, ve-hachi
nami mistabra, that makes sense, דקתני סיפא: de-katani seifa: כל הטהרות וכל
הטמאות שהיו אלו מטהרים ואלו מטמאים לא נמנו עושים טהרות אלו על
גבי אלו. Kol ha-teharos ve-kol ha-temeios she-hayu eileh metaharim ve-eileh metameim lo
nimnu osim teharos elu al gabei elu. They wouldn't be concerned about
using one another's כלים keilim for טהרות. taharos. אי אמרת בשלמא דמודי
להו, Ei amart bishlama de-modi lehu, if you say that they would
inform them, משום הכא לא נמנו. mishum hacha lo nimnu. So now
you can explain how they would borrow each other's כלים. keilim. אלא
אי אמרת לא מודי להו, Ella ei amart lo modi lehu, if
you'd say that they did not inform them, בשלמא בית שמאי מבית
הלל לא נמנו, bi-shlama Beit Shammai mi-Beit Hillel lo nimnu, so I
get that בית שמאי Beit Shammai did not hold themselves back from
using בית הלל's Beit Hillel כלים. keilim. דטמאות דבית הלל לבית שמאי
טהורות. De-tmeios de-Beit Hillel le-Beit Shammai tehoros. Things that are טמאות tmeios
to בית הלל Beit Hillel are טהורות tehoros to בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. Now this makes it sound like בית הלל Beit Hillel is
more stringent than בית שמאי Beit Shammai in טומאה וטהרה, tuma ve-tahara,
which is what רש"י Rashi says, which is not true. There are
like two פסקים where בית הלל Beit Hillel is more stringent, but
pretty much across the board בית שמאי Beit Shammai is more stringent.
So תוספות Tosafot has a reverse גרסה. girsa. Okay, so anyway, because
it is funny that it makes it sound like בית הלל Beit
Hillel is the מחמירים. machmirim. But anyway, we'll read it with our
גרסה, girsa, but the idea is if you're the מחמיר, machmir, you
understand how the מקילים mekilim can borrow from the מחמיר. machmir. Okay,
טהרות דניחא אלא בית הלל מבית שמאי למה לא נמנו טהורות לבית
שמאי לבית הלל טמאות. Teharos de-nicha ella Beit Hillel mi-Beit Shammai lamah
lo nimnu tehoros le-Beit Shammai le-Beit Hillel tmeios. But how could the
מחמיר machmir borrow from the מקיל? mekil? What the מקיל mekil thinks
is טהור tahor the מחמיר machmir thinks is טמא. tamei. אלא לאו
דמודי להו, Ella lav de-modi lehu, it must be that they inform
one another. שמע מינה. Shema mina. That's a good proof. So the
גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה. Shema mina. ומאי אולמיה, U-mai ulmih, right,
so the חידוש Chidush of the משנה Mishna is that they were
enough respectful of one another, you know, that they informed one another.
ומאי אולמיה דהאי מהאי? U-mai ulmih de-hach mei hach? So why did
you bring a breadth of proof from the case of טומאה וטהרה
tuma ve-tahara from then the case of intermarriage? So, no, you know,
either way you're saying it's clear that the only way to make
sense of this is that they informed. מהו דתימא צרה קלא אית
ליה. Mah d-teima tzara kala it lei. I might have thought that
the case of the צרה, tzara, you know, whether there's a יבום
yibum and a צרה tzara like that, it's well-known information, so they
didn't even have to inform one another. קא משמע לן. So therefore
we're telling us that even in the case of טומאה וטהרה tuma
ve-tahara where it was not well-known information, the houses went out of
their way to inform one another. So the גמרא Gemara has now
completely diffused the חידוש, chidush, the tremendous חידוש chidush of the משנה,
mishna, that they could just go ahead and like... and this is
really the question of how radical a concept of pluralism you have.
In a way, this סוגיא sugya that we're doing is really central
to a concept of like a pluralist פסק. psak You know, there
could be one thing of like a pluralist truth, אלו ואלו דברי
אלוהים חיים. Eilu ve-Eilu Divrei Elokim Chayim. But the גמרא Gemara says
אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים והלכה כבית הלל. Eilu ve-Eilu Divrei Elokim
Chayim ve-halacha ke-Beit Hillel. You know, it's one thing to say in
theory that there's multiple truths, but there's a question about like practice,
right? So how does that play out? So the first question is
that do we insist that there be uniformity of practice? So the
answer is no, we actually don't insist that there be uniformity of
practice. That in itself is a חידוש chidush that some people might
say that's anarchy. You need to have one religious community, everybody has
to be doing exactly the same thing, one authority. So here we
actually allow the idea, which is actually very true nowadays, particularly where
it's become completely decentralized, but in the past, at least in one
geographic location, there was one authority. Now it's really been decentralized, and
you have multiplicity of practices, and we don't see that that's a
threat to the idea of religious community or religious authority. But then
you have the idea, can you really live in an area of
multiple truths where I can, even though it's against my פסק, psak
I can say, well, since you פסקן that way, I'll... I'll just
follow you, even though it's not my פסק. psak. Now I do
want to say, by the way, there's a גמרא gemara in חולין
Chullin
that I mentioned to the students which is very important, which is
a חידוש chiddush because you could say I can't do something that
compromises my own intellectual integrity. But is it really about intellectual integrity?
Meaning, let's say somebody comes to you for פסק הלכה. psak halacha.
And you actually feel that something is אסור. assur. Okay, but you
know that this person in their situation needs a פסק psak, that
it's מותר. muttar. And you know that there's a different rabbi that
פסקן that it's מותר. muttar. Can you say to this person: Look,
you really don't want to be asking me this question. You need
to ask Rabbi so-and-so this question, right? Not because he knows more
than me but because he has a different פסק psak, than me.
So actually this case comes up in חולין. Chullin. Somebody goes to
Rabbi and says, is such-and-such kosher with a case that they cooked
a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh with other food in the pot? And
there's a question whether a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh gives off taste.
And he said, don't ask me this question, go to Rabbi so-and-so
who פסקן that גיד הנשה gid hanasheh that if you cook a
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh the rest of the pot is okay. So
that's also a very powerful statement about if you would like אלו
ואלו elu v'elu halakhic pluralism, that there could be multiple acceptable פסקים
at the same time and you know, and I could even say
it's not compromising my intellectual integrity because I wouldn't do it, but
I can accept that within the nature of what it means to
follow הלכה, halacha, that is an acceptable position to follow and you
are in your right to go to ask the שאלה shayla there.
I don't think that objectively that person is wrong and everybody who's
listening to that person is you know is all being עובר over
on איסורים. issurim. Okay, people who listen to that person are doing
the right הלכה. halacha. I can't because I think it's wrong. Okay,
but now in our case בית הלל Beit Hillel בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai you get to the real radical question which is, which is,
but then how did they themselves intermarry? They themselves think it's the
wrong פסק psak, and they're choosing to actually follow it. And therefore
the גמרא gemara has to tame that position and say either they
בית שמאי Beis Shammai follow בית הלל Beis Hillel or they informed
בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Now what should be noted is, is that
this is not what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks
the same question and I should have brought the ירושלמי Yerushalmi with
me and I don't have it. But the what? No, I don't
have the ירושלמי Yerushalmi on my iPhone and I need to have
the oh wait I actually do have a ירושלמי Yerushalmi here.
Just excuse me just one second. This is
really so important to read so I could summarize it for you
but let me just see if I can read it to you.
Yes, ירושלמי Yerushalmi right here, יבמות. Yevamot. Yeah,
יבמות. Yevamot. This one volume is the whole ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
Okay, so it says so it says like this, it says ממזרות
בינתים ואת אמרת הכין? Mamzeirus beintayim v'at amarta hachin? They are ממזרים
mamzeirim here and you're saying that they married one another? How did
that happen? So
היך? heich? So that's the question. So רבי יעקב בר אחא בשם
רבי יוחנן מודים בית שמאי לבית הלל לחומר, Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha
beshem Rabbi Yochanan modim Beis Shammai l'Beis Hillel l'chomer, which basically is
that בית שמאי Beit Shammai, conceded you know was מחמיר machmir like
בית הלל Beis Hillel whatever they okay. So anyway then the גמרא
gemara asks related questions and then it says like
this רבי תנחום בשם רבי יוחנן אלו ואלו כהלכה היו עושים. Rabbi
Tanchum beshem Rabbi Yochanan elu v'elu k'halacha hayu osim. So each one
followed their own
פסק. psak אם כהלכה היו? Im k'halacha hayu? Anyway it has a
similar question and then the answer
is אמר רבי יוסי
בר אבין עד שלא בא מעשה.
Amar Rabbi Yosi bar
Avin ad shelo ba maaseh. Wait a minute. No, hold on, I'm
just looking for the punchline here.
Okay, so finally then it says again ממזרות בינתים ואת אמרת הכין?
Mamzeirus beintayim v'at amarta hachin? There are ממזרים mamzeirim in this mix
and ממזרות mamzeiros and you're saying that and that and you're saying
that everybody followed their own הלכה, halacha, you know, how could that
be and then they intermarried? So the answer is המקום משמר ולא
אירע מעשה לעולם. Hamakom mishamer v'lo ira maaseh l'olam. Okay,
so God watched them and nothing ever happened. Yeah, that's sort of
now
and then the גמרא gemara goes on now. The question is well
you know what does that mean? Is that like סומכין על הנס,
somchin al haness, right? What it says but what it sounds to
say is the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually allows for the possibility that to
treat the משנה Mishnah literally and say, you know, I respect your
פסק, psak you respect my פסק, psak and we could just go
ahead and you know sort of be blind to the implications of
that you know in terms and but we'll assume that God will
make it all work out.
Okay, so you know the question is well you know what happens...
If actually it came to the fact that you married somebody and
you found out that she was a ממזרת mamzeret according to your
פסק, psak. right? What does it mean that you know God will
make it work out? So how would you deal with the facts
on the ground? And the answer could be: No, you never have
to worry about it, God's always going to make it work out.
But I know that, you know, Rav Gilad from עלי גבעות Alei
Givaot likes to talk about this ירושלמי Yerushalmi and sort of said,
argue that the basic position of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, and it's interesting
to think about some other ירושלמים Yerushalmim about this, is that we'll
make sure that it'll never work out. Meaning that if it seems
like it worked out once that a somebody from בית הלל Beit
Hillel married somebody who according to their פסק psak? was a ממזר
mamzer from בית שמאי, Beit Shammai so somehow we'll create some type
of a halachic fiction and be able to explain why she really
wasn't a ממזרת. mamzeret. And although that sounds like a little radical,
you know, we're actually going to come up later in the, not
to ruin the surprise for later, but later in the מסכת, masechet,
much later towards the end, where the גמרא gemara deals with a
case where a,
you know, there were witnesses that said the woman's husband died. She
went and married another man, and then of course the husband shows
up, there're like movies like that, right? Anyway, so the בבלי Bavli
deals with all these implications or whatever, but there's a position in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says: No, that guy isn't her husband.
So, he totally looks like, he has all this evidence, he says:
Doesn't matter, clearly he's not her husband because the witnesses said the
husband already died. You know, so the ability to sort of create
a legal fiction in the face of evidence is something actually that
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is more prepared to do than the בבלי, Bavli,
even when there's like blatant evidence against it, but still to stick
to maintain that legal fiction. So his claim was, was that's also
the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi's answer, he didn't connect it to the later ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, but his claim was that that's also the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi's answer
over here. By the way, some people might know that there's a
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says, you know, the גמרא gemara says that if
a young girl, I mean again, it's so harsh talking about these
cases, under the age of three has sex, the hymen will grow
back, but over the age of three the hymen won't grow back.
So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says if she had sex over the age
of three, because it was just her birthday, but her birthday was
in אדר, Adar, and then they made a leap year, so it
worked out that after the fact it wasn't her birthday yet because
there was a, you know, so they put in a second אדר,
Adar, then it will grow back. So, now of course, you could
sort of say that that means that בית דין Beit Din has,
you know, creates metaphysical realities or physical realities, but it could also
be about insisting about a sort of halachic fiction, like legal statement,
you know, that we will insist on even in the face of
counter-evidence. So it's interesting that the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi's answer is here: You
know what? They did it and it all worked out, you know,
and compared rather than the way the בבלי Bavli tries to sort
of reconcile it by saying: They informed, they didn't do it, and
so on. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi is prepared to say they did it.
Yes.
Isn't it current practice for the ממזר mamzer situations that you really
do everything in your power by rabbinic authority?
Yes, yes, exactly. And we certainly try to do that by ממזר
mamzer situations a lot. And then the question is, I guess, just
questions: What's the breaking point? You know, till what point? Okay.
This is a issue of
כרת, kares, from the more weighty forbidden acts. Yes, and we'll discuss
that later.
Yes, but isn't it interesting what to make of it, that this
entire discussion in which the ending is, you know, they informed each
other, was introduced in the relationship between רב אבא Rav Abba and
the servant?
Oh, that's interesting.
That's interesting. Maybe the גמרא Gemara was preparing us for that answer
somehow. Yes.
And בית הלל Beit Hillel holds that
not just the classical forbidden ones as a ממזר, mamzer, but also
if you have this, the child of a צרה tzara is a
ממזר mamzer also?
No, only if, no, no,
that would not be a ממזר, mamzer, it's only because this woman
according to בית הלל Beit Hillel is not obligated in יבום, yibbum,
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that you do יבום, yibbum, and
therefore it's an איסור אשת אח. issur eshet ach. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: גופא. gufa. Now let's go back actually to look at that.
אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar אף על פי שנחלקו בית שמאי
ובית הלל בצרות af al pi shenechleku Beit Shammai uBeit Hillel betzarot
מודים שאין ממזר אלא ממי שאיסורו איסור ערוה modim she'ein mamzer ela
mimi she'issuro issur erva וענוש כרת. ve'anush kares. Okay, so מאן מודים,
man modim, who's conceding to whom here? אילימא בית שמאי לבית הלל,
Ilima Beit Shammai leBeit Hillel, so if it means that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai will concede that there's not a ממזר mamzer case in
בית הלל Beit Hillel scenario. בית הלל Beit Hillel scenario for בית
שמאי Beit Shammai meaning for בית הלל Beit Hillel they would say
this woman doesn't require חליצה chalitza and she would go marry another
man, בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say she requires חליצה chalitza of
the צרה. tzara. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai will say: Well, we
don't, at least we're not going to consider the kid a ממזר
mamzer because it's an איסור לאו. issur lav. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says: פשיטא בני חייבי לאוין נינהו, Pshita bnei chayavei lavin ninhu,
nobody would ever question that the kids would be okay. You don't
need to concede the point that the kid isn't an ערוה erva
here. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא בית הלל לבית שמאי, Ella
Beit Hillel leBeit Shammai, so בית הלל Beit Hillel concedes to בית
שמאי Beit Shammai that it's only a ממזר mamzer if it's an
איסור כרת. issur kares. Okay, but it is an איסור כרת issur
kares because בית שמאי Beit Shammai did יבום yibbum with the צרה.
tzara. So היא גופא חייבי כריתות היא. hi gufa chayavei keritot hi.
So, you know, so which... Which is the case that it says
they concede, like that there's a חידוש chiddush to the point that's
being made here? So the גמרא Gemara says ולעולם בית שמאי לבית
הלל. V'lo'olam Beit Shammai l'Beit Hillel. Now בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
conceding to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, meaning בית שמאי Beit Shammai is
saying hey you guys בית הלל, Beit Hillel, if this woman goes
out who we think needs חליצה, chalitzah, we'll at least admit that
the kid won't be a ממזר. mamzer. So the גמרא Gemara says,
but isn't that obvious, it's only an איסור לאו? isur lav? לאפוקי
מדרבי עקיבא. L'afukei mid'Rabbi Akiva. No, but to show you that nobody
is concerned for רבי עקיבא's position. דאמר יש ממזר מחייבי לאוין. D'amar
yesh mamzer m'chayavei lavin. רבי עקיבא holds there is a ממזר mamzer
from חייבי לאוין. chayavei lavin. קא משמע לן דאין ממזר מחייבי לאוין.
Ka mashma lan d'ein mamzer m'chayavei lavin. They're saying that it's not
a ממזר mamzer מחייבי לאוין. m'chayavei lavin. Now תוספות points out that
even within רבי עקיבא, there's a question if he would even he
would go so far by the case of יבמה לשוק, yevamah l'shuk,
but anyway, that's the point that's being made. At least at בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, the kids of the צרות tzaros of בית הלל
Beit Hillel for בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say are certainly not
ממזרים, mamzeirim, nobody's concerned for רבי עקיבא. תא שמע. Now we're still
back to trying to figure out whether בית הלל Beit Hillel follow
whether בית שמאי Beit Shammai kept to their position or not. אף
על פי שנחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל בצרות, Af al pi shenechleku
Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel b'tzaros, even though they disagreed in our case
by צרות, tzaros, ובאחיות, u'v'achayot, cases of sisters, we'll see that sort
of later. I'm not going to go into that. It's going to
come up in a later משנה. mishnah. בגט ישן, B'get yashan, גט
ישן get yashan is a case about a guy who wrote a
גט get and then he slept with his wife before delivering the
גט. get. So does that invalidate the גט? get? ובספק אשת איש,
U'v'safek eishet ish, a woman who's in a doubtful situation. Question in
רש"י Rashi what that is, but one suggestion that רש"י Rashi has
is that is that the person delivered a גט get to his
wife that would take effect like a year from now. So her
status between now and a year from now is somewhat up in
abeyance. In abeyance, and he wants to understand that that would be
a debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel בית שמאי Beit Shammai what
her status would be.
I'm sorry, it would be effective now, but retroactively.
Yeah, so that's the whole question. Or maybe it starts now and
finishes later, that's all these discussions in גיטין. Gittin. ובמגרש את אשתו
ולנה עמו בפונדק, U'v'megaresh et ishto v'lanah imo b'fundak,
a man divorced his wife and then after they divorced, they spent
the night together in an inn. Do we think that being together
in the inn meant that they had sex? And if they had
sex, that it was sex for the sake of קידושין kiddushin and
they're remarried or not? So what's her status now?
גט ישן Get yashan is when they definitely slept together
and then, but then he divorced her. He had written the גט,
get, slept together and divorced her. Here he divorced and then they
were in the inn together. ובכסף ובשוה כסף בפרוטה ובשוה פרוטה, U'v'chesef
u'v'shaveh chesef b'prutah u'v'shaveh prutah, how much money it requires to do
קידושין. kiddushin. בית שמאי Beit Shammai, says the cost of a דינר,
dinar, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says the cost of a פרוטה,
prutah, much less. So obviously you could understand a woman might be
considered married according to בית הלל Beit Hillel, but not according to
בית שמאי Beit Shammai. because somebody only gave her a פרוטה. prutah.
Right? And by the way, the classic case the גמרא Gemara says
is that you could have something where like woman one was married
with a פרוטה, prutah, and then, sorry, ראובן Reuven gave רחל Rachel
a פרוטה prutah and then שמעון Shimon gave רחל Rachel a דינר
dinar for קידושין. kiddushin. So according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel רחל
Rachel is married to ראובן, Reuven, and according to בית שמאי, Beit
Shammai רחל Rachel is married to שמעון. Shimon. And if she sleeps
with the other man, right, it's an איסור, isur, not just כרת,
kares, חייב מיתה, chayav misah, whatever, it's adultery, the kid would be
a ממזר. mamzer. So you know, you can't say one is מיקל
meikel and one is מחמיר. machmir. You gotta come up with a
פסק psak? there, right? Okay, anyway, even though they had this debate,
לא נמנעו בית שמאי מלישא נשים מבית הלל ולא בית הלל מבית
שמאי, lo nimne'u Beit Shammai milisa nashim mi'Beit Hillel v'lo Beit Hillel
mi'Beit Shammai, they didn't hold themselves back to you know to intermarry.
לקיים מה שנאמר האמת והשלום אהבו. L'kayem mah shene'emar ha'emet v'hashalom ahavu.
ללמדך שחיבה וריעות נוהגים זה בזה, L'lamedcha shechibah v're'ut nohagim zeh bazeh,
that love and friendship you know they show to one another, לקיים
מה שנאמר האמת והשלום אהבו, l'kayem mah shene'emar ha'emet v'hashalom ahavu, love
both truth and peace. It's not, you know, often it's our choice,
right? You stand for truth, and then you know no matter what
anybody says that opposes me, I can't tolerate your position because it's
wrong, you know? Or it's, but on the other hand peace sometimes
is seen as a compromise for truth because if we make peace,
I have to concede something that I don't really believe in, okay?
And here they're saying they were able to do both. So by
the way, there's a beautiful מהרש"א Maharsha there. He says, he says
it's not אמת לאמיתו, emes l'amito, which means like there's only one
absolute truth, but it is a pluralistic אמת. emes. It's an אמת
emes of אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים. eilu v'eilu divrei elokim chayim.
So were able to have peace and truth if you can buy
into an idea that there could be multiple truths. And that allows
for that idea. Now of course, the nice way to read that
is that they ממש mamash intermarried and that you really could live
in a world of multiple halachic truths, even if it's not my
truth and I don't have to worry about it, you know.
Never heard that before then, because before you said they informed each
other. Right.
Well so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, so
I'm just saying the פשט pshat of this ברייתא, braisa, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does with it. רבי שמעון אומר נמנעו הן
מן הוודאי ולא
נמנעו
מן הספק.
Rabbi Shimon omer nimne'u hen min ha'vadai v'lo nimne'u
min ha'safek.
No, no, no.
If a woman was a וודאי vadai אסור, asur, then they would
not intermarry. But if she was only a case of a ספק,
safek, like the question about you know husband and wife that slept
in the inn, do we have to think that they that they
became remarried or not, and there's a debate that was about some
doubt, then I could say well I could follow your פסק psak
because at the end of the day this we all admit that
there's a ספק safek here what happened. The question is just are
we מחמיר machmir for the ספק safek or מיקל? meikel? Then I
could sort of tolerate your פסק. psak But if it's like a
question of this woman who's married is she married to ראובן Reuven
is she married to שמעון Shimon and according to one it's definitely
one the other it's definitely... the other, how could you tolerate the
other person's פסק? psak So right, and our משנה's mishna not a
ספק. safek. Okay, so let's take a look. אי אמרת בשלמא
עשו, Ee amarta bishlama asu,
so if every house followed its own position, so משום הכי נימנעו,
mishum hachi nimnu, so now you understand why Rabbi Shimon said that
they held themselves back in a case of a ודאי. vaday. אלא,
Ela, of course we have to understand the first half of the
משנה mishna which says they didn't hold themselves back. אלא אי אמרת
לא עשו, Ela ee amarta lo asu, but if they didn't keep
to their own position,
so אמאי
נימנעו, amay nimnu, why would they have held themselves back in a
case of ודאי vaday if everybody anyway is following one פסק? psak
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברה, Vitisbara, one minute, does that make
sense? ניהי נמי דעשו, Nihi nami de'asu, let's say they kept their
own positions. בשלמא בית הלל נימנעו מבית שמאי דחייבי כריתות נינהו
וממזרים הם. Bishlama Beit Hillel nimnu miBeit Shammai dechayvei keritot ninhu u'mamzerim
heim. So we understand why בית הלל Beit Hillel would not marry
into the kids of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai, Again, the גמרא's Gemara.
primarily focusing on the צרה tzara case. תוספות points out that this
question could go both ways as we just raised a range of
different debates. But within the צרה tzara debate, we would get why
בית הלל Beit Hillel? would not marry into בית שמאי Beis Shammai
because the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. דחייבי כריתות נינהו וממזרים הם de'chayvei
keritot ninhu u'mamzerim heim לבית הלל. le'Beit Hillel. Okay, אלא בית שמאי,
ela Beit Shammai, but in the case again of the צרה tzara
case, אמאי נימנעו מבית הלל? amay nimnu miBeit Hillel? Why would they
not intermarry with בית הלל? Beis Hillel, Meaning Rabbi Shimon says they
wouldn't intermarry in the case of ודאי. vaday. Why not according to
Rabbi Shimon? The kids are not ממזרים. mamzerim. What's the issue? בני
חייבי לאוין נינהו וכשרין נינהו. Bnei chayvei lavin ninhu uksherin ninhu. They're
only איסור לאו issur lav and the kids are okay. So again,
why does Rabbi Shimon say they wouldn't intermarry? קשיא. Kashya. So here
the answer, we have an answer: כדאמר רב נחמן בר יצחק לא
נצרכה אלא לצרה עצמה. Kede'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak lo nitzrecha ela
le'tzara atzma. Like Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak's going to say later, no,
the kids wouldn't be a problem for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai but
the woman herself was a problem. That's an איסור לאו. issur lav.
You don't want to be עובר over on an איסור לאו. issur
lav. So he's going to say that about another case, so say
it here too.
הכא נמי לא נצרכה אלא לצרה עצמה. Hacha nami lo nitzrecha ela
le'tzara atzma. Okay. Now, ומאי שנא מודאי דאיסורא
הוא? U'mai shna mi'vaday de'issura hu? So why would they not intermarry
in a case of ודאי? vaday? Because it's an איסור, issur, because
it's a ממזר, mamzer, an איסור לאו, issur lav, you don't want
to be עובר over on an איסור, issur, you know that from
your פסק this woman is definitely forbidden. ספק נמי איסורא הוא. Safek
nami issura hu. So since when are you allowed to disregard doubtfully
איסורא? issura? Even if it's a ספק, safek, but you don't want
to be עובר over on a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, you know,
on a ספק אשת איש. safek eshet ish. So again, it's funny
that the גמרא Gemara here had an open, you could have said
that we allow ourselves to believe that at least in a case
of ספק, safek, at least it'll have worked out properly, you know,
and that's the whole point that's being made here. Certainly the ירושלמי's
Yerushalmi idea that God is going to make it work out could
work in a case of ספק. safek. Okay, but the בבלי Bavli
doesn't want to accept that. Okay, so I can't complain, ספק safek
also doesn't make sense. So the גמרא Gemara says לא תימא מן
הספק אלא אימא מן הסתם. Lo teima min hasafek ela eima min
hastam. All right, it doesn't mean that they would intermarry in the
case of doubt, אלא אימא מן הסתם. ela eima min hastam. They
would intermarry in a case where things were not, had not, you
know, it hadn't been, it wasn't explicit that the woman was forbidden.
But it doesn't mean it was a doubt. What it means was
דמודעו להו פרשי. demodeu lehu parshi. It means again, back to our
answer, so that they would be informed and they would not intermarry.
Now that's not סתם, stam, that's that they know definitely the opposite.
So רש"י Rashi slightly reframes it and says that since you would
be informed, the other house, when there was a problem, if you
didn't say anything, they could assume it was okay. Which then for
that is a slightly bigger חידוש. chiddush. I know that in your
community there are women walking around that I think are ממזרות. mamzerot.
Nevertheless, I could go ahead and date whoever I want, engage whoever
I want, and I'll just assume that if there's a problem, somebody's
going to let me know. So I don't have to investigate because
I'll assume that you'll inform me if there is a problem. So
again, that creates a greater sense of mutual respect and trust and
so on, that you don't even have to ask, you can just
assume that a סתם stam case is okay or else somebody would
have told you otherwise. So he says ולא נימנעו מן הספק. ve'lo
nimnu min hasafek. It doesn't mean that a ספק איסור safek issur
like the case of sleeping together in the inn and was she
remarried or not. It means they would not hold themselves back from
marrying a woman that they didn't know what her story was, because
they would assume that as long as I don't know what the
story was, it's okay. If it weren't okay, somebody would tell me.
Okay.
Hire a woman?
Did I say hire? Marry. Marry a woman. Okay, anyway, so marry.
So ולא נימנעו היינו מן הסתם ve'lo nimnu hainu min hastam in
our משנה? mishna? What? So ולא נימנעו ve'lo nimnu means in our
משנה, mishna, right, it means,
it means women, right, in general. Because and that's ולא נימנעו. ve'lo
nimnu. Meaning, so
now according to ודאי, vaday, it's a better פשט pshat in the
משנה. mishna. המשנה Hamishna isn't ולא נימנעו ve'lo nimnu because before I
would date any woman, somebody would tell me her story. ולא נימנעו
Ve'lo nimnu means I could just go ahead and date any woman
I would want to because I would know that if there were
a problem, somebody would let me know. Okay, so that does create
that greater sense of concern for the other, everybody else's position that
you're going to proactively let... somebody now and I can assume I
don't have to worry about it. I can assume people will let
me know if there's a problem.
You'd have an obligation to let someone know?
Well, yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, גמרא. Gemara מותיב
ליה פפא Motiv lei Pappa and now we got as Michael says
better פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishna. You could just סתם stam
intermarry because you assume you'll be informed otherwise. ומה קא משמע לן?
u'mai ka'mashma lan? דאהבה ורעות נוהגים זה בזה. d'ahava v're'ut nohagim zeh
bazeh. So now it's sort of like Michael's question, if you're informing
what's the חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש chiddush is that you have so
much love and friendship and concern that you go out and that
I can that I know that you'll let me know if there's
a problem and I don't have to actually proactively investigate.
But you would let the other person know too because you're concerned.
Right and I'll let you know if there's a problem. We'll make
sure. So היינו רישא, hainu reisha, so that's what the beginning of
that ברייתא Braita set, אמת emes you know to tell you that
שלום ואהבה נוהגת. shalom v'ahava noheget. So the גמרא Gemara says הא
קא משמע לן דכולה רבי שמעון היא. ha ka'mashma lan d'kula Rabi
Shimon hi. The whole ברייתא Braita is רבי שמעון. Rabi Shimon. Now
what you might not be aware that the גמרא Gemara just did
is it also neutralized the whole beginning of the ברייתא Braita because
the whole beginning of the ברייתא Braita said straight they would just
go ahead and intermarry. רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon said oh no only
in a case of ספק safek not a case of וודאי. vadai.
So the פשט pshat is that the beginning of the ברייתא Braita
says they would intermarry even in a case of וודאי, vadai, right,
even in a case where you definitely was a problem they would
intermarry. So the גמרא Gemara has completely neutralized that by making the
whole ברייתא רבי שמעון Braita Rabi Shimon and saying רבי שמעון Rabi
Shimon is not disagreeing he's just clarifying that the beginning of the
ברייתא Braita that says they would intermarry is being clarified to mean
only in a case of ספק safek not in a case of
וודאי. vadai.
In a case of סתם stam not even ספק. safek.
Right
and ספק safek means סתם stam correct.
And even though רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon was appearing in the end
of the ברייתא Braita he's
really the author of the whole ברייתא. Braita. But again the funny
thing is the גמרא never even spelled out the real challenge of
the beginning of the ברייתא. Braita. The פשט pshat is the beginning
of the ברייתא Braita says even in a case of וודאי vadai
right and the גמרא has completely glossed over that.
Because in ספק ספיקא דאורייתא לחומרא. safek sfika d'Oraita l'chumra.
Yeah but we've made it no longer
ספק.
safek. Right it's סתם. stam. It's in a case that's where ספק
safek wouldn't work. ספיקא דאורייתא לחומרא. sfika d'Oraita l'chumra.
Right so now correct so now what we have done is we
have all of this evidence that seems to be meaning other than
רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon who seems to distinguish ספק safek and וודאי.
vadai. The פשט pshat of this evidence is they could blithely go
ahead and intermarry and not worry that it's against their פסק and
the consequences of that. And the גמרא has tamed it first trying
to say well maybe בית שמאי Beis Shammai practiced like בית הלל,
Beis Hillel? that's too wild to say. So fine they kept their
own practices but we said but at least they let each other
know and now it's ratcheted up a level to at least say
and because they would let each other know they didn't have to
inquire. Okay they would know that they would have been informed and
that at least is a better way you can read the משנה
Mishna more כפשוטו k'pshuto you know in that spirit but that's at
least how the גמרא is able to tolerate this idea. Okay תא
שמע come and hear דאמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי d'amar Rabi Yochanan
ben Nuri
היכא הלכה רווחה בישראל? heicha halacha revacha b'Yisrael? How should we spread
normally הלכה רווחה בישראל halacha revacha b'Yisrael means that this is the
consensus this is what everybody does. But he's sort of asking up
more of a proactive question what is the הלכה halacha that we
should propagate in Israel regarding this debate of צרת ערווה? tzaras ervah?
Should we basically try to get everybody to פסקן like בית שמאי
Beis Shammai or should we get everybody to פסקן like בית הלל?
Beis Hillel. Either way you're going to be a problem from the
other perspective and here you get already this idea of trying to
take a let's try to figure out how to פסקן לכל הדעות
pasken l'chol hadeios idea. Okay how should we propagate this הלכה halacha
in Israel? נעשה כדברי בית שמאי naaseh k'divrei Beis Shammai let's go
like בית שמאי and say the צרת ערווה tzaras ervah you know
can do יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitza. הולד ממזר לדברי בית הלל.
havlad mamzer l'divrei Beis Hillel. So if people will do יבום yibum
you'll have ממזרות mamzerus according to בית הלל. Beis Hillel Right. נעשה
כדברי בית הלל naaseh k'divrei Beis Hillel let's go like בית הלל
Beis Hillel. you don't have to worry about יבום yibum or חליצה.
chalitza. הולד פגום לדברי בית שמאי. havlad pagum l'divrei Beis Shammai. The
kid we've been saying the kid isn't a ממזר mamzer but a
kid still as a child of an איסור לאו issur lav would
at least be a problem for a כהן. Kohen. Now we're going
to analyze that later but let's now just accept it. And anyway
even if the kid isn't a problem for a כהן Kohen the
woman is אסור. assur. So you know you're not going to get
one פסק that everybody's going to agree to. Let's just go by
the higher standard. There is no higher standard. Each פסק is a
problem for the other position.
They should follow
the הלכה halacha of בית הלל. Beis Hillel So בוא bo okay
but he's still was dealing with obviously okay I mean that is
a good question you know maybe this was sort of before the
בת קול. bas kol. Okay or maybe he's just saying that something
as weighty as this we want there to be some consensus for.
So בואו ונתקן להם לצרות שחולצות ולא מתייבמות. bo'u v'nesaken lahem l'tzaros
shecholtzos v'lo misyabmos. We quoted this before. I got the solution. Every
time you got this everybody do חליצה. chalitza. And therefore בית הלל
Beis Hillel is happy בית שמאי is happy because חליצה chalitza was
done. בית הלל you know they might not be happy they would
say חליצה chalitza wouldn't be necessary but at least their concerns they're
not hurt. Now of course she's hurt because she now is אסור
assur to a כהן. Kohen. There's a cost at this but at
least this way the woman is not you know it's going it's
going to be free and clear according to everyone. Okay so it's
like I heard I've heard some people that they want to solve
the current I heard this from more than one person. They're brilliant
no they're brilliant solution to solve the the what do you call
it the גירות geirus issue you know in Israel or whatever is
just to say I have the solution every single person for their
בר ובת מצוה bar v'bas mitzvah should just go ahead and do
a גירות geirus and then
and then and then everyone everyone will be you
know. Everybody do a
חליצה *chalitzah*. Okay, anyway, so לא הספיקו לגמור את הדבר *lo hispiku
ligmor es hadavar*. This was his solution. But you know, it is
a good question: why not just הלכה כדברי בית הלל *halacha k'divrei
Beis Hillel*? But again, maybe this was before that was solidified and
this was very wavy. So this was his solution. Have everybody do
חליצה *chalitzah*. לא הספיקו לגמור את הדבר *lo hispiku ligmor es hadavar*
until נטרפה השעה *nitrefa hasha'ah*. They didn't have a chance to finally
decide it, like he was getting everybody ready to come to this
consensus and this vote, and then something happened and like, you know,
they lost their opportunity. Okay, they had an opportunity and they lost
it, which might be a good thing because, you know, there's a
real cost to this type of a position. Right, which people don't
appreciate. יוצא כל הדעות *yotzei kol hadeos* is an a- a halachic
approach that has costs to it. So אמר ליה רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *amar lei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*, so now רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* said, מה נעשה לצרה ראשונה מעתה *mah
na'aseh l'tzara rishona mei'ata*? What are we going to do now for
the original צרות *tzaros*? Meaning, so now you've got, so, and if
you take a look, this is actually why there was opposition to
this position. Not because of the cost to the from here on
in, the cost to the women that's going to be חליצה *chalitzah*
for בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, you're going to אסור *assur* them to
a כהן *kohen* that was unnecessary. But also, what this is going
to do retroactively to how we look at the past. Look at
רש"י *Rashi*: מה נעשה לצרות ראשונות שנתייבמו ובניהם ממזרים אם נגמור הלכה
שלא יתייבמו *mah na'aseh l'tzaros rishonos shenisyabmu uvneihem mamzerim im nigmor halacha
shelo yisyabmu*. So he's concerned, at least the first way the גמרא
*Gemara* reads this, according to the implications now for בית הלל *Beis
Hillel*, for בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*. The women according to בית שמאי
*Beis Shammai*, you're basically making a statement that ייבום *yibbum* is not
allowed, you have to do חליצה *chalitzah*. So that's going to get
everybody to look at the- at the children from בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai*, at the women who did ייבום *yibbum* with בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai* as problematic, and the children as problematic. Now to me, that's
not- I don't really understand that question so much. If you're doing
חליצה *chalitzah*, you're saying that implicitly ייבום *yibbum* is a possibility. It
doesn't necessarily mean that you look askance at the previous women who
did ייבום *yibbum*. But that's at least we'll see how the גמרא
*Gemara* is going to rephrase, but that's his question. If you're going
to insist that everybody does חליצה *chalitzah*, what's it going to do
to the earlier צרות *tzaros* that have had ייבום *yibbum* done with,
you know, that have- have done ייבום *yibbum*? אי אמרת בשלמא *ei
amart bishlama*, and let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* does with this.
עשו *asu*, that בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* did their thing and בית
הלל *Beis Hillel* did their thing, היינו דקאמר מה נעשה *hainu d'ka'amar
mah na'aseh*. That's what he's going to say, he's saying now you
want to sort of change the פסק *psak* and make a consensus,
what's going to be the implications about the past? So there's going
to be implications about the past because each school did their own
thing in the past. אלא אי אמרת לא עשו *ela ei amart
lo asu*, but if the בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* did not do
the- their own position and followed בית הלל *Beis Hillel*, מאי מה
נעשה *mai mah na'aseh*? So what does it mean, oh, what about
the implications of the past? What do you mean implications of the
past? In the past everybody's been doing like בית הלל *Beis Hillel*.
What's the big deal? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak*, לא נצרכה אלא לצרה עצמה *lo nizrecha ela l'tzara atzma*.
So no, we're not concerned about the case of like the kids
and ממזר *mamzer* etc. We're concerned- and this is the line we
quoted before- we're concerned about the implication to the צרה *tzara* herself.
So everybody until now has been going like בית הלל *Beis Hillel*.
This is the idea, בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* has been following בית
הלל *Beis Hillel* and everybody's been treating this woman as not obligated.
But ומה נעשה הכי קאמר *umah na'aseh hachi ka'amar*, הנך צרות דבית
הלל לבית שמאי היכי נעביד להו *henach tzaros deBeis Hillel leBeis Shammai
heichi na'avid lehu*? These women that were צרות *tzaros* for בית הלל
*Beis Hillel*, what should בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* do? ליחלצו *lichlezu*.
Now so you've got this- here's the scenario.
Okay, you have these women, everybody's been according to the scenario that
everybody's been following בית הלל *Beis Hillel*. All these cases of צרות
*tzaros*, so they went ahead and they married other men without- without
חליצה *chalitzah*, right? Because בית הלל *Beis Hillel* said that they were
completely free and clear, yes? Everybody got that scenario? Comes along רבי
יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri* and says, yeah, but it's
sort of ignoring בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*. What we should do from
now on is insist that all these cases everybody does חליצה *chalitzah*.
Okay, that's what רבי יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri* is
suggesting. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* is saying, what
about all those women that are already married without חליצה *chalitzah*? You're
going to insist they do חליצה *chalitzah*, so you're saying two things:
first of all,
you're implying that there still was some זיקה *zika* or whatever, some
problem, and you're going to- it's going to be des- you know,
destructive to basically say, oh, you're all married, but you know what,
you never really were freed from your previous brother-in-law, you gotta all
do a חליצה *chalitzah*. So that's what he means. What is going
to be the implications now you want to start playing things safe,
what's going to be the implications for the facts on the ground?
Okay? So he says, הנך צרות דבית הלל לבית שמאי היכי נעביד
להו ליחלצו *henach tzaros deBeis Hillel leBeis Shammai heichi na'avid lehu lichlezu*,
let them do חליצה *chalitzah*. מי מסיא גבריהו *mi masya gavreihu*? They'll
become like disgusting to their husbands. Okay, meaning they'll say, ugh, I've
been sleeping with a woman, I've been married to a woman who
really was a- you know, her- sort of זיקה *zika* to another
man, really wasn't מותר *mutter* to me fully yet. וכי תימא לימאסן
*vechi teima limasan* and they say, okay, big deal, let's just live
with the cost, but this way we'll play it safe, okay, because
everybody's concerns get taken care of. No, דרכיה דרכי נעם וכל נתיבותיה
שלום *dracheha darchei noam vechol nesivoseha shalom*, the Torah's the ways of
pleasantness. And again, I've got to tell you, this comes up all
the time in areas of גירות *geirus*. Somebody comes... Basically says I
had a conversion. I had a conversion, this was the story, that
was the story, and the rabbi will say, and this happens really
all the time nowadays because of this centralization that's happened in the
last ten years, and everybody thinks, oh, well, we've centralized it, we've
stayed at higher standards, this is going to be better for everybody
because we'll insist on higher standards for everybody. Like this, high standards
for everybody, right? Everybody will follow, everybody will do חליצה *chalitzah*, we'll
play it safe. Okay, but then you go and you say, yeah,
but you know what, why don't you do a גירות *geirus* again
לחומרא *l'chumra*? It's not a big deal, just take another dunk in
the מקוה *mikvah*. You know, you've been married for ten years, you've
got kids or whatever. Yeah, yeah, but we're just going to play
it safe. What's the big deal? Just go to the מקוה *mikvah*,
take a dunk, you and your kids. You know, it's all done.
Of course, as the גמרא *Gemara* says, just do a חליצה *chalitzah*,
no big deal. Of course, that completely
ignores the human, emotional, and sort of religious implications of insisting on
those things and what messages it sends about the person and their
status and so on. What message are you sending to this couple
about your wife, you know, that she needs a חליצה *chalitzah*? Oh,
but we're playing it safe, we're just going to make sure that
everybody's happy, playing it safe. Playing it safe comes at very often
at very great human costs. Okay, and it's very important that that's
sort of the point here, that in the end they didn't go
and say let everybody do חליצה *chalitzah*. You know, to do it
now would create a cost, make all the women אסור *assur* to
כהן *Kohein*, and we'd also create a serious cost about the facts
on the ground. So the answer is that you cannot ignore those
costs just for the sake of playing it safe. That's why פסקנינג
*paskening*, you פוסק *pasken* a position and you follow it. You know,
it's not an idea that you just try to מתפשט *mitpasha* that
you cover all your bases.
Okay, so we will continue with this.